Guide to the Charles E. Jordan Papers, 1942 - 1966
Duke University. University Archives
Charles E. Jordan papers 1942 - 1966
Jordan, Charles E., 1901-1974.
Duke University. Office of Public Relations.
28.5 linear feet, Extent: 19000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Charles E. Jordan (1901-1974) served Duke as Assistant Secretary from 1925 to 1941, as Secretary from 1941 to 1957, as Chairman of the Athletic council from 1949 to 1963, and as Vice President for University Relations from 1946 to 1966. He was also active in community organizations, including the Durham County and North Carolina Boards of Education and various Methodist Church organizations. Jordan retired from Duke in 1966. The collection includes correspondence, subject files, audiotape, and other records relating to administrative and athletic matters at Duke University. Major subjects include scholarships, public relations, intercollegiate athletics (NCAA, ACC, Southern Conference, Duke Athletic Council, and Duke Athletic Association), the Angier B. Duke Memorial Scholarship Program, the Woman's College, and university publications. There are also materials relating to the proceedings of the North Carolina Conference of the Methodist Church and to educational matters in Durham and North Carolina. English.
UA.29.02.0076
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Charles E. Jordan Papers was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1965, 1966, 1971, 1972.
Biographical Note
Charles E. Jordan was born in Henrietta, N.C. in 1901. He received his A.B. from Trinity College in 1923 and his law degree from Duke in the spring of 1925 (in the first class to graduate from Duke law school.) He served Duke as Assistant Secretary from 1925 to 1941, as Secretary from 1941 to 1957, as Chairman of the Athletic council from 1949 to 1963, and as Vice President for Public Relations from 1946 to 1966. He was also active in community organizations, including the Durham County and North Carolina Boards of Education and various Methodist Church organizations. These activities are reflected in his papers. Jordan retired from Duke in 1966. He died in 1974. Durham's Jordan High School was named after him in 1963.
Collection Overview
The collection includes correspondence, subject files, audiotape, and other records relating to administrative and athletic matters at Duke University. Major subjects include scholarships, public relations, intercollegiate athletics (NCAA, ACC, Southern Conference, Duke Athletic Council, and Duke Athletic Association), the Angier B. Duke Memorial Scholarship Program, the Woman's College, and university publications. There are also materials relating to the proceedings of the North Carolina Conference of the Methodist Church and to educational matters in Durham and North Carolina.
Subject Headings
Atlantic Coast Conference; College sports -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Duke University. Athletic Association; Duke University. Athletic Council; Duke University. Dept. of Athletics; Duke University -- Funds and scholarships; Duke University -- Public relations; Duke University -- Sports; Duke University. Woman's College; Jordan, Charles E., 1901-1974; Methodism -- North Carolina; National Collegiate Athletic Association; Southern Conference
Contents of Collection
- Subject files 1942-1966
  These materials were received in several separate accessions and are shelved in the same order as they were received. Within each accession, subject files are arranged chronologically. To facilitate research and the location of files, all folders are presented in this finding aid in alphabetical order with their corresponding box numbers.
  - A Correspondence (Box 33)
  - A Correspondence, 1942-1948 (Box 1)
  - A Correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - A Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 20)
  - Administrative Committee (Box 1)
  - Administrative Committee Minutes, 1958-1960, [3 folders] (Box 34)
  - Administrative Committee, 1956-1960 [3 folders] (Box 33)
  - Administrative Committee--Correspondence from President (Box 20)
  - Admissions, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - Admissions--Undergraduate Policy Committee (Box 34)
  - Advancement--Staff Minutes (Box 34)
  - Alumni Loyalty Fund (Box 1)
  - Alumni Meetings (Box 1)
  - Alumni Meetings--Loyalty Fund Trips (Box 20)
  - Alumni Office--C. A. Duke (Box 1)
  - Alumni Office--C. A. Dukes Miscellaneous Correspondence [2 folders] (Box 34)
  - Alumni Office--C. A. Dukes Miscellaneous, 1950-1959 [2 folders] (Box 20)
  - Alumni Offices--Renovation (Box 20)
  - Alumni Visits (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors--Duke Chapter (Box 20)
  - American Library Association (Box 35)
  - American Social Hygiene Association (Box 1)
  - Annual Giving--City of Durham Participation (Box 20)
  - Applications (Box 1)
  - Appointments Office (Box 35)
  - Archives Committee (Box 1)
  - Athletic Academic Averages, 1952 (Box 20)
  - Athletic Association, 1951-1953 (Box 52)
  - Athletic Association, 1953 (Box 52)
  - Athletic Association. General correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 52)
  - Athletic Council, 1928 (Box 52)
  - Athletic Council, 1949-1963 [8 folders] (Box 52)
  - Athletic Council. Audits, Peat, Marwick & Mitchell 1949-1962 [9 folders] (Box 52)
  - Athletic Council. Football coach. Applications and correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 52)
  - Athletics (Box 1)
  - Athletics - newspaper clippings (Box 52)
  - Atlantic Coast Conference, 1953-1963 [18 folders] (Box 53)
  - B Correspondence (Box 35)
  - B Correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 2)
  - B Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 21)
  - B-Bn Correspondence, 1942-1948 (Box 1)
  - Band Room--YMCA Chapel (Box 2)
  - Band--Band Day (Box 21)
  - Baptist Student Union (Box 21)
  - Basketball Coach Applications (Box 35)
  - Baylin Trophy, 1952-1955 (Box 52)
  - Bequest Program (Box 21)
  - Bo-Bu Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees (Box 21)
  - Board of Trustees (Box 35)
  - Board of Trustees--Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees--Reports to, etc. (Box 2)
  - Bosley, Harold A. (Box 2)
  - Boy Scouts (Box 2)
  - Boy Scouts (Box 21)
  - Bureau of Public Information (Box 2)
  - Bureau of Public Information (Box 35)
  - Bureau of Public Information, 1952-1955 (Box 21)
  - C Correspondence (Box 35)
  - C Correspondence, 1941-1948 (Box 2)
  - C Correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 3)
  - C Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 21)
  - Chanticleer, 1940-1944 [5 folders] (Box 3)
  - Chapel Administrative Committee (Box 36)
  - Cherry, Gregg R. (Gastonia, NC) (Box 22)
  - Cl-Cu Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Class of 1923--Letters re: Loyalty Fund (Box 17)
  - Class of 1923--Reunion (Box 17)
  - Commencement (Box 36)
  - Commencement, 1952-1956 (Box 22)
  - Commencement, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Commission on Church Union (Box 22)
  - Commonwealth of Children Symposium (Box 36)
  - Conference Survey and Long-Range Planning Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 22)
  - Congratulations, Letters of (Box 3)
  - Curriculum Administration (Box 36)
  - D Correspondence (Box 36)
  - D Correspondence, 1941-1951 [2 folders] (Box 4)
  - D Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 22)
  - Daniels, Captain Thomas C. (Box 4)
  - Degrees Awarded and Lists of Candidates, 1945-1958 [3 folders] (Box 36)
  - Degrees Awarded--Summary, 1925-1953 (Box 22)
  - Development Office [2 folders] (Box 37)
  - Development Program (Box 4)
  - Development Staff Minutes (Box 37)
  - Divinity School (Box 4)
  - Duke Hospital (Box 5)
  - Duke Hospital (Box 22)
  - Duke Memorial Church, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Duke University Church (Box 5)
  - Duke University Day (Box 5)
  - Duke University Loyalty Fund--Area Meetings (Box 5)
  - Duke University National Council (Box 5)
  - Dukes, C. A., 1949-1951 (Box 5)
  - Durham Broadcasting Enterprises, Inc. (Box 22)
  - Durham Chamber of Commerce (Box 5)
  - Durham Chamber of Commerce (Box 37)
  - Durham Community Fund (Box 5)
  - Durham County School Board (Box 5)
  - Durham District Stewards--District Work, 1941 (Box 5)
  - E Correspondence (Box 37)
  - E Correspondence, 1942-1951 [2 folders] (Box 6)
  - E Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 23)
  - Edens, President (Box 6)
  - Enrollment Statistics (Box 37)
  - F Correspondence (Box 38)
  - F Correspondence, 1942-1951 [2 folders] (Box 6)
  - F Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 23)
  - Faculty Committees (Box 38)
  - Faculty Senate (Box 6)
  - Faculty, General (Box 6)
  - Faculty--General (Box 38)
  - Few, William Preston--Papers and Addresses (Box 6)
  - Flowers, Robert Lee (Box 6)
  - Football Letters (Box 38)
  - Founders' Day (Box 6)
  - G Correspondence (Box 38)
  - G Correspondence, 1942-1951 [2 folders] (Box 7)
  - G Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 23)
  - Graduate School (Box 7)
  - Graduate School (Box 38)
  - H Correspondence (Box 38)
  - H Correspondence, 1942-1951 [2 folders] (Box 7)
  - H Correspondence, 1952-58 [2 folders] (Box 23)
  - Heart Drive (Box 24)
  - Hoey, Senator Clyde R.--Correspondence re: Papers (Box 24)
  - Homes and Hospitals, Board of (Box 7)
  - I Correspondence (Box 38)
  - I Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 8)
  - Inauguration of President (Box 8)
  - Inauguration--A. Hollis Edens (Box 8)
  - Institutional Advisory Committee (Veteran's Administration) (Box 8)
  - Inter-Conference Commission (Box 8)
  - Invoices--Miscellaneous (Box 38)
  - J Correspondence (Box 39)
  - J Correspondence [2 folders] (Box 8)
  - J Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 24)
  - Jordan File (Box 39)
  - Jordan's Personal Correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box 8)
  - Jordan's Personal Correspondence, 1950-1954 (Box 9)
  - K Correspondence (Box 39)
  - K Correspondence [2 folders] (Box 9)
  - K Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 24)
  - L Correspondence (Box 9)
  - L Correspondence (Box 39)
  - L Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 24)
  - Lake Junaluska (Box 39)
  - Lake Junaluska Assembly (Box 10)
  - Lake Junaluska, 1949-1951 (Box 10)
  - Lake Junaluska, 1952-1955 (Box 24)
  - Library (Box 39)
  - Library--Technical Services Dept. (Box 39)
  - Loans, Correspondence re: (Box 24)
  - Long Range Planning Committee, 1960 (Box 40)
  - Long Range Planning Report, 1958-1959 (Box 39)
  - Loyalty Fund (Box 40)
  - M Correspondence (Box 40)
  - M Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 24)
  - M Correspondence, [3 folders] (Box 10)
  - Mc Correspondence (Box 10)
  - Mc Correspondence (Box 40)
  - Mc Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 24)
  - Medical Care and Life Insurance--Fringe Benefits (Box 40)
  - Medical School Admissions (Box 40)
  - Medical School--Admissions and Rejections (Box 10)
  - Medical School--Correspondence re: Admissions [4 folders] (Box 11)
  - Medical School--Correspondence re: Admissions, 1951-1954 (Box 25)
  - Meetings to be held at Duke (Box 11)
  - Methodist Board of Publications--NC CHRISTIAN ADVOCATE, 1949-1958 [2 folders] (Box 25)
  - Methodist Church General Board of Education (Box 25)
  - Methodist Church [NC Conference]--S. E. Journal of the Methodist Church (Box 27)
  - Methodist College Advance (Box 11)
  - Methodist College Foundation (Box 11)
  - Methodist College Foundation, 1948-1957 [2 folders] (Box 25)
  - Methodist Council--World (Box 26)
  - Methodist Fund, Inc., 1956 Oct.-1957 Oct. (Box 26)
  - Methodist Student Center (Box 26)
  - Methodist Student Center--Correspondence, 1952-1958 [3 folders] (Box 26)
  - Methodist Student Center--Equipment Fund (Box 26)
  - Methodist Student Chaplain--Fellowships, 1950-1958 [2 folders] (Box 27)
  - Methodist Student Work (Box 11)
  - Methodist Youth Fellowship (NC Conference)--Annual Conference Sessions (Box 27)
  - Minah, T. W. (Box 11)
  - N Correspondence (Box 40)
  - N Correspondence [2 folders] (Box 12)
  - N correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 27)
  - National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA), 1949-1963 [11 folders] (Box 52)
  - National Council of Churches of Christ--Committee on the Use and Understanding of the Bible (Box 27)
  - National Resources Conference (Box 27)
  - National School Boards Association, Inc. (Box 27)
  - News Service--Boyden-Fike (Box 12)
  - Non-graduate Admissions (Box 12)
  - North Carolina Christian Advocate--Editor's Home (Box 27)
  - North Carolina FM Radio Education Committee (Box 12)
  - North Carolina Library Association, 1954-1957 [2 folders] (Box 28)
  - North Carolina Press Association (Box 40)
  - North Carolina Press Association Dinner, 1950-1951 [2 folders] (Box 12)
  - North Carolina Press Association, 1951-1957 [2 folders] (Box 28)
  - Nursing School Admissions (Box 41)
  - O Correspondence (Box 12)
  - O Correspondence (Box 41)
  - Occidental Life (Box 42)
  - Occidental Life Insurance [4 folders] (Box 41)
  - Occidental Life, 1955-1958 (Box 28)
  - Orange Bowl, 1953-1957 (Box 52)
  - P Correspondence (Box 42)
  - P Correspondence [2 folders] (Box 12)
  - P Correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 13)
  - P Correspondence, 1951-1955 (Box 28)
  - Payroll [2 folders] (Box 42)
  - Plyer, A. W.--Donor of E. Lee Prize (Box 42)
  - President's Reports, 1955-1962 [6 folders] (Box 43)
  - President, Reports to, 1952-1955 (Box 28)
  - Public Relations, Applications for Position in (Box 28)
  - Q Correspondence (Box 43)
  - R Correspondence (Box 43)
  - R Correspondence, 1942-1951 [2 folders] (Box 13)
  - R Correspondence, 1951-1955 (Box 29)
  - Registrar's Office (Box 44)
  - Reinsch, Miss Ute (Box 29)
  - Report on Higher Education and Dollar Support, 1961 Jan. (Box 29)
  - Retirement Plan (Box 13)
  - Retirements (Box 44)
  - Reynolds Student Investment Trust (Box 29)
  - Rotary Club Programs, 1956 Jan. (Box 29)
  - Rotary Foundation Scholarship (Box 29)
  - Rural Churches (Box 14)
  - Rural Churches, Committee on (Box 14)
  - S Correspondence (Box 44)
  - S Correspondence [2 folders] (Box 14)
  - S Correspondence, 1947-1951 [3 folders] (Box 15)
  - S Correspondence, 1952-1959 [3 folders] (Box 29)
  - Sample, Paul (Box 30)
  - Sands, Alex Jr. [2 folders] (Box 15)
  - Scholarship Fund, General--Contributions, 1945-1950 [2 folders] (Box 16)
  - Scholarship--A. B. Duke Report, 1959-1960 (Box 45)
  - Scholarship--W. N. Reynolds (Box 44)
  - Scholarships--A. B. Duke Memorial--Summaries (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Alyse Smith (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Angier Duke Regional (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Dr. D. M. Litaker (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Ed Guest Class Christian Education (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--George M. Ivey (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--H. H. Jordan Memorial Foundation (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--High Point Alumni (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Holmes-McCausland Trust Loan Foundation (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--J. Welch Harris (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--James E. Shepard Memorial Foundation (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Mayer (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--McMullen (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 44)
  - Scholarships--Miscellaneous Correspondence [3 folders] (Box 45)
  - Scholarships--Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1952-1958 [2 folders] (Box 30)
  - Scholarships--Ottis Green Foundation Fellowship (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Pan-Hellenic (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Rochelle (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Special Scholarship Committee, 1949 (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--Student Correspondence and Lists, 1949-1950 [2 folders] (Box 15)
  - Scholarships--U. S. Steel Foundation, Inc.--Contributions (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--W. N. Reynolds Loan and Scholarship Fund (Box 16)
  - Scholarships--W. P. Few (Box 16)
  - School of Missions--Women's Society of Christian Service (Box 30)
  - Seaboard Airline Railroad (Box 30)
  - Separk, J. H.--Memorial Scholarship Fund (Box 30)
  - Smith, W. Herbert (Box 30)
  - Smith, Willis [2 folders] (Box 30)
  - Southern Conference, 1948-1952 [5 folders] (Box 52)
  - Southern Conference, 1951-1953 [5 folders] (Box 53)
  - Southern School News (Box 31)
  - Special File (Box 45)
  - Student Affairs, 1955-1956 (Box 31)
  - Summer Session, 1952-1958 [2 folders] (Box 31)
  - Summer Sessions (Box 45)
  - Summer Sessions (Box 46)
  - T Correspondence (Box 46)
  - T Correspondence [2 folders] (Box 17)
  - T Correspondence, 1952-1958 [2 folders] (Box 31)
  - Teacher Education in Duke University, Centennial Celebration of (Box 31)
  - Television (Box 17)
  - Television (Box 31)
  - Trinity College and College of Engineering--Correspondence (Box 31)
  - Trinity College and College of Engineering--Correspondence re. Admissions, 1952-1955 [2 folders] (Box 32)
  - Trinity College, College of Engineering Admissions, 1958-1962 [4 folders] (Box 46)
  - Trinity College, Correspondence re: Admissions (Box 17)
  - Trinity College, History of, 1839-1842 (Nora Chaffin), Correspondence re:, 1950-51 (Box 17)
  - Tuition (Box 46)
  - Tuition Increase, Letters re:, 1946-1948 [2 folders] (Box 17)
  - U Correspondence (Box 18)
  - University Council [3 folders] (Box 47)
  - University Faculty Committee on Elections, 1952-1956 [4 folders] (Box 47)
  - University Faculty--Notices, Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 47)
  - University House (Box 32)
  - University Religious Council (Box 48)
  - University Students, Official Lists of, 1954-1956 [2 folders] (Box 48)
  - V Correspondence (Box 48)
  - V Correspondence [2 folders] (Box 18)
  - W Correspondence [4 folders] (Box 18)
  - W Correspondence, 1952-1958 [3 folders] (Box 48)
  - Washington and Lee University, 1960 May 7 (Box 49)
  - Woman's College, Duke University--Mrs. Persons Correspondence (Box 18)
  - Woman's College--Admissions Correspondence, 1952-1957 [5 folders] (Box 49)
  - Woman's College--Admissions Correspondence, 1956-1962 [6 folders] (Box 50)
  - Woman's College--Candidates for Degrees (Box 51)
  - Woman's College--Correspondence re: Admissions, 1947-1951 [2 folders] (Box 19)
  - Woman's College--Directories and Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 51)
  - XYZ Correspondence (Box 19)
  - XYZ Correspondence (Box 51)
Related Material
Biographical Reference Collection: Charles E. Jordan
Duke University Archives
News Service Biographical Files: Charles E. Jordan
Duke University Archives
Athletic Council Records, 1907-1993
Duke University Archives